<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Enterprise Management">
  
	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Enterprise Management (EM) Essential Security Requirements</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership (NIAP)</maintainer>
		<identifier>00x</identifier>
		<version>0.9x</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>27 June 2025</issuedate>
		<approver/>
		<supercedes/>
	</intro>

	<section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
		<p>
		This document describes a core set of security requirements for Enterprise Management (EM) systems.  These requirements cover basic security characteristics and behaviors for an EM system. 
		</p><p>
		EM systems are used by EM administrators to manage endpoint devices in an enterprise. EM systems typically consist of an EM server and may include endpoint host agents.
		</p><p>
		The intent is that the remaining sections provide succinct statements that highlight the relevant aspects to be addressed by the Technical Community (TC) contributing to the PP. Here, the authors provide a narrative that introduces the reader to the problem being solved, and present key aspects that support or guide the TC and may elaborate on subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level statements.
		</p>
	</section>
	<section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
		Enterprise Management (EM) products in scope for this PP should have functionality of at least one, but potentially some combination of the following use cases, in order to enable EM administrators to manage endpoints. 
		<br/><br/>
		<ul>
			<li>[USE CASE 1] Interfacing with Endpoints – enables EM administrators to manage endpoints by issuing commands to push, edit, or retrieve data; for example, this may include:
				<ul>
					<li>deploying software (system software like operating systems, application software, or software updates) to endpoints,</li> 
					<li>setting configurations/policies on endpoints, </li>
					<li>running custom scripts on endpoints to automate other management tasks,</li> 
					<li>or interactive remote access of endpoints.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
		<li>[USE CASE 2] Storing Data – database(s) of endpoint device data that can be queried or browsed; for example, this may include an inventory of the following across endpoints:
		<ul>
			<li>software,</li>
			<li>hardware,</li>
			<li>or configuration/policy.</li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		<li>
		[USE CASE 3] Monitoring – allows for monitoring through notifications, alerts, and potentially automating other actions (e.g. remediation steps) based on endpoint states; for example, this may include monitoring for states like:
		<ul>
			<li>low disk space, </li>
			<li>high memory usage, </li>
			<li>account creations, </li>
			<li>accounts being added or removed from groups,</li> 
			<li>or services stopping.</li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
    	<ul>
    		<li>Sensitive data stored by the EM system.</li>
    		<li>Credentials for authentication to or from the EM system.</li>
    		<li>Cryptographic key material used to perform secure communications with host agents.</li>
    		<li>Sensitive data in transit to or from the EM system.</li>
    	</ul>
    	
	</section>

	<section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess"> 
		Attackers are assumed to have:
		<ul>
		•	network access with the EM server and the endpoint devices. 
		o	An attacker could exploit the lack of secure communication to communicate with, intercept and modify communications between, or eavesdrop on communications to EM system components. For example, an attacker could 
			issue commands to endpoints (like deploy arbitrary policies and/or software).
			 
		•	local non-privileged access to the endpoint devices or EM server. 
		o	An attacker could access or modify data stored by the EM system. For example, an attacker with access to the EM server could try to view or change authentication credentials to the management interface. 
		•	physical access to endpoint devices. 
		o	An attacker could access data stored on the endpoint device. 
		</ul>
		 
		
		**********************************************************
		
		<ul>
			<li>An attacker can impersonate the EM server on the network or issue commands to endpoints, for example to deploy policies and/or software.</li>
			<li>An attacker can exploit the lack of secure communication between the EM server and host agents or endpoints.</li>
			<li>An attacker could access or modify data stored by the EM system.</li>
			<li>An attacker with access to the EM server can view or change authentication credentials to the management interface.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	

	
	<section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
		<ul>
		<li>General mitigations 
			<ul>
			<li>Updates to the EM system
				<ul>
				<li>The EM server/agents shall have a mechanism to report patch levels and initiate the patching process.</li>
				<li>Updates shall be cryptographically signed such that the platform can verify authenticity prior to installation.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Configuration of EM system
				<ul>
				<li>Host agent and EM server statuses</li> 
				<li>The EM server shall allow configuration of agent heartbeat and/or reporting intervals.</li>
				</ul>
			</li> 
			<li>Anti-exploitation features
				<ul>
				<li>EM system binaries shall use anti-exploitation capabilities (ASLR, DEP, etc.) provided by the platform on which the EM system runs</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			</ul>	
		</li>
		<li>Authentication and Authorization
			<ul>
			<li>Identities shall be authenticated and authorized prior to accessing or modifying sensitive data, based on authentication mechanisms provided by the platform or EM system</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li>Confidentiality and Integrity of data at-rest and in-transit 
			<ul>
			<li>Communications between EM server and endpoint devices shall be cryptographically secured - for example, remote administration and audit features must employ cryptographic algorithms to secure communications</li>
			<li>Sensitive stored data shall be cryptographically secured</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li>Auditing and Compliance
			<ul>
			<li>Auditing capabilities for all EM system components shall include
				<ul>
				<li>events like administrative actions, commands issued to endpoints/endpoint host agents, EM system errors</li>
				<li>resiliency of auditing, for example, local storage of audit logs if an endpoint agent loses connectivity to the server</li>
				<li>audit logs must be accessible outside the EM system, for example able to be forwarded (SIEM, email, syslog, etc.) or exported</li>
				<li>accountability of actions taken (identity information, date/time, action)</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		<li>The EM server/agents shall have a mechanism to report patch levels and initiate the patching process.</li>
		<li>Architecture
		<ul>
			<li>Resiliency
				<ul>
				<li>Failover</li> 
				<li>Load balanced</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Endpoint and Agent Management
				<ul>
				<li>Role-based access control</li>
				<li>Agent revocation</li>
				<li>The EM server shall configure agent heartbeat and/or reporting intervals.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>		
			<li>Permission Segregation
				<ul>
					<li>Role based Tier model, protecting privileged accounts and resources from non-privileged.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Compliance
				<ul>
				<li>Accountability of actions taken by the EM system</li>
				<li>Auditing capabilities for all EM system components, including
					<ul>
					<li>of events including: administrative actions, commands issued to endpoints/endpoint host agents, EM system errors</li>
					<li>resiliency of auditing – for example, local storage of audit logs if an endpoint agent loses connectivity to the server</li> 
					<li>audit logs must be accessible outside the EM system, for example able to be forwarded (SIEM, email, syslog, etc.) or exported</li>
					</ul>			
				</li>
				<li>Able to search data and make reports</li>  
				<li>Security events search criteria</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Confidentiality and Integrity
				<ul>
				<li>Cryptographically securing communications between EM server and endpoint devices, particularly for sensitive communications</li>
				<li>For example, remote administration and audit features must employ cryptographic algorithms to secure communications</li>
				<li>Cryptographically securing sensitive stored data</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Risk Management
				<ul>
					<li>Ties into architecture with custom defense strategies based on the capabilities of the architecture</li> 
					<li>Zero Trust for all EM system components – verifying authentication and authorization, for example for accessing or modifying sensitive</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
		The following assumptions are made for the EM software product and its operational environment. The Enterprise Management Software is not expected to provide any assurance in any of these areas, and as a result, requirements are not included to mitigate the associated threats.
		<ul>
		<li>A.PLATFORM<br/>
		The TOE relies upon a trustworthy computing platform with a reliable time clock for its execution. This includes the underlying platform and whatever runtime environment it provides to the TOE.</li> 
		<li>A.PROPER_ADMIN<br/>
			The Administrator of the software solution is not careless, wilfully negligent or hostile, and administers the software within compliance of the applied enterprise security policy.</li>
		<li>A.PROPER_USER<br/>
		The user of the application software is not willfully negligent or hostile, and uses the software in compliance with the applied enterprise security policy.</li>
		<li>A.PHYSICAL_PROTECTION<br/>
		The Enterprise Management Software is physically protected in its operational environment and not subject to physical attacks that compromise the security or interfere with the host device’s physical interconnections or ability to operate at full capacity. This protection is assumed to be sufficient to protect the data contained within the Enterprise Management Software solution.</li>
		<li>A.REGULAR_UPDATES<br/>
			The Enterprise Management Software is assumed to be updated by an Administrator on a regular basis in response to the release of product updates due to known vulnerabilities.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Optional Extensions" id="extensions"> 
		None defined
	</section>

	<section title="Outside the TOE's Scope" id="outsidescope">
	  <!--
			This is where the authors explicitly state things they do not want 
			to be considered for inclusion in an evaluation against a 
			resulting PP.  Items expressed here could include threats, 
			functions or capabilities that would require assurance activities 
			that are too subjective, or specific expertise not available in the
			evaluation facilities expected to assess products against the PP 
	  -->
		
		Threats out of scope of this PP include attackers with:
		<ul>
			<li>local privileged access to the endpoint device and/or EM server.</li>
			<li>physical access to the EM server.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
</ESR>
